{"tossups": [{"question": "Fundraising for this monument included the creation of 5 million half-dollar coins that depicted two chatting soldiers on horseback. North Carolina governor Angus McLean offered protection from extradition to Gutzon Borglum, who fled arrest in 1925 after being fired from the design of this monument and destroying his models. This monument, the world\u2019s largest bas relief, is the centerpiece of a park that opened on the 100th anniversary of Abraham Lincoln\u2019s assassination. For ten points, name this controversial Georgia monument that honors three Confederate leaders.", "answer": "<b> Stone Mountain</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country\u2019s national dish consists of a mix of chili peppers and cheese called Ema datshi. In the Battle of the Five Lamas, invaders were blown up while trying to loot this country\u2019s Simtokha Dzong. This country, which banned climbing its mountain Gangkhar Puensum, was led until 2006 by King Jigme Singye Wangchuck, who coined the term Gross National Happiness. Druk the Thunder Dragon is featured on the flag of, for ten points, what Himalayan nation ruled from Thimphu?", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Bhutan</b> (or<b> Druk Yul</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Joseph Rosa is considered the chief biographer of this man, who allegedly killed a bear with a knife to allow a freight train to continue its journey to Santa Fe. This man killed the leader of the McCanles Gang during a fight at a Pony Express Station. Hays and Abilene were the Kansas cities where this man served as marshal. Jack McCall murdered this man at a saloon in Deadwood while he held two black eights and two black aces during a game of poker. For ten points, name this Wild West folk hero known for carrying the \u201cdead man\u2019s hand.\u201d", "answer": "James Butler \u201cWild Bill\u201d<b> Hickok</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Poet Christine de Pisan used this art form to show Reason, Justice, and Rectitude as crown-wearing women building a wall in<em> The Book of the City of Women</em>. The earliest depiction of Thomas Beckett\u2019s murder is one of these works, which are characterized by marginalia and vibrant initials interspersed throughout the text. For ten points, name these medieval books filled with gold and silver embellishments and illustrations.", "answer": "<b> illuminated</b> manuscript (accept word forms like<b> illumination</b>; prompt on \u201cpainting,\u201d\u201cdrawing,\u201d \u201cbook,\u201d or \u201cmanuscript\u201d)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "As Governor of New York, this man signed an act to gradually abolish slavery that, despite stating children of slaves were free, forced them into decades of indentured servitude. In 1795, this man negotiated the removal of British troops from the Northwest Territory with a treaty fixing many of the issues of the earlier Treaty of Paris. With Alexander Hamilton and James Madison, this man wrote the Federalist Papers. For ten points, name this first Chief Justice of the United States.", "answer": "John<b> Jay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country carried out Operation Cerberus to successfully extract its ships from the port of Brest. The<em> Glorious</em> was sunk by a 27,000 yard shot from one of this country\u2019s<em> Scharnhorst</em>-class battleships. At the Battle of the Denmark Strait, the<em> Prince of Wales</em> and<em> Hood</em> were defeated by this country\u2019s <em>Prinz Eugen</em> and<em> Bismarck</em>. For ten points, name this country whose navy attacked Allied shipping using wolf-packs of U-boat ships.", "answer": "Nazi<b> Germany</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A meteorological agency monitors 59 secret locations for the initial presence of these items. Specimens of the Yoshino variety of these organisms have been proven to be genetically identical to each other, making disease a risk. Maps track a namesake \u201cfront\u201d of these items, which are produced from trees in the genus<em> Prunus</em> and are appreciated in a custom called<em> hanami</em>. Springtime crowds flock to Japan to see, for ten points, what types of flowers, otherwise known as<em> sakura</em>?", "answer": "<b> cherry blossom</b>s (accept<b> sakura</b> before mentioned; prompt on \u201ccherry trees\u201d before \u201ctrees\u201dis read)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "This work\u2019s printer, Robert Bell, added the phrase \u201cwritten by an Englishman\u201d without the author\u2019s permission. Royalties from this work were anonymously donated to the Continental Army. One section of this work comments on the absurdity of an island ruling a nation, and another argues that the colonies have enough resources to rival the navy of Great Britain. For ten points, name this pamphlet written in 1776 by Thomas Paine.", "answer": "<b> Common Sense</b> BONUS:<em> Common Sense</em> wasn\u2019t Paine\u2019s only pamphlet to be popular in America and controversial in England; British authorities suppressed this three-part pamphlet that championed deism and attacked the divine nature of the Bible. ANSWER: The<b> Age of Reason</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Prohibition Party candidate in this election year faced the Portland Rum Riot as mayor. Neal Dow and Greenback Labor candidate James Weaver ran in this year, whose losing major party candidate was known \u201cThunderbolt of the Army of the Potomac\u201d for his heroism at Gettysburg. The winner of this election year was a compromise candidate for the Half-Breeds and Stalwarts and was succeeded a year later by his running mate, Chester Arthur. For ten points, name this election year in which Winfield Scott Hancock lost to James Garfield.", "answer": "U.S. presidential election of<b> 1880</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Through their contact with China, these people introduced the seax shortsword to Western Europe, and they adopted the Alani practice of lengthening of the skull of infants born to noblemen. These people lost the Battle of Nedao, and a coalition of the Visigoths led by King Theoderic and Romans under Flavius Aetius defeated these people at the Battle of Catalaunian Fields in 451 AD. For ten points, name these nomadic people led by the so-called \u201cScourge of God,\u201d Attila.", "answer": "<b> Hun</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man, who gained most senior status after the retirement of Anthony Kennedy, is now often considered the farthest right on the political spectrum of the current court. Sexual harassment against Anita Hill did not prevent the confirmation of, for ten points, what justice who assumed Thurgood Marshall\u2019s seat on the Supreme Court and is known for his general silence during arguments?", "answer": "Clarence<b> Thomas</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This story\u2019s postscript warns that \u201che that runs races with goblin troopers will have rough riding of it.\u201d The tendency of married men to linger about the taverns in this story\u2019s setting give it the nickname Tarry Town. This story\u2019s protagonist rides the horse Gunpowder and competes with the character Brom Bones for the affection of Katrina Van Tassel. For ten points, name this story from<em> The Sketch Book</em> <em>of Geoffrey Crayon</em> featuring a cursed Hessian soldier and the schoolmaster Ichabod Crane, written by Washington Irving.", "answer": "The<b> Legend of Sleepy Hollow</b> (do not accept or prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The losing side in this battle allegedly began to throw oranges and lemons after running out of usable weapons. In this battle, Marcantonio Colonna withstood an attack from Uluc Ali\u2019s fleet in the Gulf of Patras in this battle, which was preceded by a siege of (+) Famagusta. Author Miguel de Cervantes lost an arm fighting in this battle, the last major battle of (*) </b> rowing ships. The Real [ray-AHL] served as the flagship of Don Juan of Austria, the winning commander of, for ten points, what 1571 battle, a massive naval defeat for the Ottoman Empire?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Lepanto</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This event concluded with Patrick Sarsfield\u2019s retreat at the Battle of Reading [redding]. A successful invasion of Torbay, crucial to the beginning of this event, was followed by</b> <b>support from the (+)</b> <b>Immortal Seven. Organizers of this event had been angered by the</b> <b>Immortal Seven. Organizers of this event had been angered by the</b> <b>Declaration of Indulgence, which sought to achieve religious tolerance for (*)</b> <b>Declaration of Indulgence, which sought to achieve religious tolerance for (*)</b> Catholics. A \u201cProtestant wind\u201d helped facilitate the crossing of the English Channel during, for ten points, what relatively peaceful revolution in which James II was overthrown by William and Mary as rulers of England?", "answer": "<b> Glorious Revolution</b> (accept<b> Revolution of 1688</b>; prompt on Bloodless Revolution; prompt on descriptive answers relating to William & Mary invading England and/or James II being deposed)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man and his sons killed James Doyle, two of Doyle\u2019s sons, and two other men in a May 24th, 1856 attack that was inspired by the sacking of Lawrence a week prior. The (+) Pottawatomie Massacre was led by this man, who declared that he was \u201cquite certain\u201dthat America\u2019s crimes will \u201cnever be purged away but with blood\u201d on the morning of his (*)</b> hanging in 1859. Robert E. Lee led a Marine detachment that ended this man\u2019s brief occupation of a federal armory, which he had hoped would lead to an armed slave uprising. For ten points, name this violent abolitionist who led the raid on Harper\u2019s Ferry.", "answer": "John<b> Brown</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In 1823, Bella Salomon gifted a complete manuscript of one of this composer\u2019s works to Felix Mendelssohn, whose staging of the piece five years later kicked off a (+) revival of this man\u2019s work. This composer presented a set of six instrumental works to Margrave Christian Ludwig, and a melody by Frederick the Great was used as the basis for this composer\u2019s </b><em><b>Musical Offering</b></em><b>. This composer\u2019s many (*)</b> sons included the composers Carl Phillip Emmanuel and Johann Christian. The<em> Brandenburg Concertos</em> were written by, for ten points, what German Baroque composer, the oldest of the \u201cThree B\u2019s\u201d?", "answer": "Johann Sebastian<b> Bach</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This event was triggered by an accident involving barrels of benzol. Vince Coleman sent a telegram reading \u201cHold up the train. [...] Guess this will be my last message. Good-bye boys.\u201d, which saved hundreds of passengers from riding directly into this event. A (+) half-ton piece of metal that was thrown over 2 miles away is now a monument to this event; that metal was part of the anchor of the SS (*) </b> <em>Mont Blanc</em>, whose cargo caught fire. For ten points, name this December 6, 1917 tragedy in which over 2,000 people were killed in Nova Scotia in the largest pre-nuclear, man-made explosion in history.", "answer": "<b> Halifax explosion</b> (accept descriptions of the SS<b> Mont Blanc explosion</b> before mentioned;\u201cexplosion\u201d not needed after mentioned; prompt on other descriptive answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The Supreme Court ruled in</b><em><b> Cooper v. Aaron</b></em><b> against this city\u2019s plan to wait over two years to implement a proposal by Virgil Blossom. Ronald Davies issued a desegregation</b> <b>order in this city, which led to an iconic photo of (+)</b> <b>Elizabeth Eckford. This city\u2019s</b> <b>mayor, Woodrow Wilson Mann, sent a telegram asking for federal troops to President (*) </b>Eisenhower. Governor Orval Faubus tried to thwart the<em> Brown v. Board</em> decision at Central High School in, for ten points, what city where, in 1957, nine black students helped desegregate public schools in Arkansas?", "answer": "<b> Little Rock</b> (accept<b> Little Rock</b> Nine)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}